Ken Ham CEO of Answers in Genesis and
creator of the world's only life-sized
biblical Arc except for the real one of
course apparently watched my recent
YouTube video detailing some of the
reasons why I don't believe in god let's
take a look now we go into a different
clip and this one by a person called
Alex O'Connor
we're sometimes told that God has
morally sufficient reason to allow
suffering to exist indeed if God is good
then he must have such sufficient reason
perhaps suffering is necessitated by
human Free Will perhaps suffering helps
to develop a person's moral character or
maybe it's necessary to achieve some
other end that God wishes to bring about
but intuitively there appear to be
instances of suffering that cannot serve
any such end I clip after clip after
clip of people like this that I see
talking about the deaf and suffering
issue just don't get it that this is not
the world as God made it this world is
suffering from our sin and God judged
this he's a holy God and he judges with
death in fact we don't even deserve to
exist I mean we deserve nothing because
we and Adam sinned against a holy God is
this not the world as God made it
remember Ken Ham believes that the story
of Genesis is a literal account of
actual his historical events is God not
responsible for creating the serpent
that tempted Eve causing sin to
supposedly enter the world that's not to
absolve her of moral responsibility for
violating God's commandment not to eat
of the tree but think about it Ken is
responding here to the problem of evil
and suffering by saying that the world
is not as God made it so surely he means
one of two things he might mean that the
world as God created it contained no
evil or he may mean that it contained no
suffering that these things only pervade
the world because of Adam and Eve's sin
well if the world as God made it
contained no evil then how did it
contain within it an evil deceptive
serpent it seems to me like evil did
exist in the Garden of Eden before any
man ever sinned indeed it must have
because otherwise there would have been
no evil to tempt Eve and thus no fool
perhaps then Ken means that before the
fool there was no suffering but this
doesn't seem right either we have an
indication in Genesis that suffering did
exist before the fall since when Eve
does sin God punishes her saying I will
greatly multiply your pain in
childbearing the Hebrew word here is
usually translated as multiply meaning
to increase implying that childbirth was
already a somewhat painful experience
even before Eve sinned so we can't
explain the existence of suffering on
account of man's sin either thus in
responding to the problem of evil and
suffering by saying remember this is not
the world as God made it what can Ken
Ham mean it appears that the world as
God did make it contained both evil and
suffering before the fall of Man however
Ken has subtly changed the language here
I was talking in my speech about
suffering he's introduced the concept of
death and God judged this he's a holy
God and he judges with death now he may
wish to say that it was death which
entered the world through Adam's sin and
that's fine but if that's what he means
then he's simply not responding to my
arguments since I never mentioned death
at best this would allow him to explain
why humans are mortal but not why they
suffer during their lives that's not to
mention of course the suffering of
non-human animals plus God warns Adam in
Genesis by saying but off the tree of
the knowledge of Good and Evil you shall
not eat for in the day that you eat of
it you shall die
in the day that you eat of it
interesting given that Adam is said in
Genesis 5 to have lived for 930 years
surely then death here can't mean
literal death or the same day can't mean
literally the same day otherwise Adam
would have literally died the same day
that he sinned well that's easy maybe
death here just means something like
becoming mortal or spiritual death or
something like that
strange though for kenham if a talking
snake just has to be literal but death
or the same day are not we don't even
deserve to exist I mean we deserve
nothing because we and Adam sinned
against a holy God but he allows us to
exist and really when you look at this
world that we live in this Fallen World
it it's a reminder of how bad our sin is
how how much we have rejected our
creator he brought us into existence and
we rebelled against him so kenham is
implying here that the reason for death
and suffering in the world remember he's
responding to the problem of evil is
because of man's sin principally through
Adam and Eve the doctrine of original
sin usually contains some idea that
human beings today inherit a sinful
State something like a propensity
towards sinning from Adam and Eve
because they committed a first original
sin but how can sin have entered the
world through sin if before the fool
humans didn't have a proneness to sin
then how can Eve before the Fall have
been so prone to sinning that she did so
after a single conversation with the
serpent it seems like it wasn't Adam and
Eve who bestowed upon humans a tendency
to sin but God himself since that
tendency was already there before the
fool and indeed was responsible for the
fool and so if not sin or a proneness
towards sinning what exactly was
inaugurated by Adam and Eve's eating of
the fruit what is it that entered the
world and was transmitted from them to
us through this original sin
suffering but it's implied that that was
already there evil that was definitely
already there in the serpent death or
perhaps but then what has this got to do
with the problem of suffering Augustine
thought that before the fool Adam and
Eve had the choice to sin or not to sin
but that after the fall humans no longer
have the option not to sin and that it's
this that was transmitted to us but this
suggestion makes it seem even more
grotesque to me to be punished on
account of sin since we now have no
choice but to do so and there are
further problems let's look again at the
full narrative Genesis tells us that God
commands Adam not to eat of the tree of
the knowledge of Good and Evil for if he
does so then he will die the serpent
then comes to Eve and says look he will
not die God just knows that if you eat
it you'll be like him knowing good and
evil then Eve sees that the fruit of the
tree looks nice and perfectly edible and
so she takes a bite and then she gives
some to Adam thus sin enters the world
or something oftentimes critics point
out that it's unfair for us to be
punished today for the sin of somebody
else a long time ago the response is
usually something like we're not guilty
of Adam's specific sin but guilty of our
own sins only we're judged for the sins
that we commit it's just that we
inherited a sinful nature from Adam and
Eve this seems perfectly plausible
indeed in Ezekiel 18 we find the words
the one who sins is the one who will die
the child will not share the guilt of
the parent nor will the parent share the
guilt of the child but now consider what
happens next in the Genesis narrative
after the fruit is eaten what is God's
response well he punishes the snake by
forcing him and his descendants to crawl
upon their belly and eat dust for all of
their lives he punishes Eve by making
childbirth an extremely painful ordeal
for her and her descendants and
subjugates her to her husband he
punishes Adam by forcing him and his
descendants to gloriously toil for the
rest of their existence in order to eat
and live
okay so the reason why childbirth is
painful for women today is because Eve
committed a sin thousands of years ago
what does this mean it means that we are
being punished now for a sin that we did
not commit in other words even if we
don't inherit the guilt of our parents
we do seem to inherit the punishment for
their crime a final problem is this Adam
and Eve were told not to eat of the tree
of the knowledge of Good and Evil
presumably this means that before doing
so they didn't have a knowledge of Good
and Evil they were in a state of
Innocence therefore when the serpent
came to tempt Eve how could she have
even possibly realized that any evil was
at work if she hadn't eaten of the tree
yet then her actions can't have been
knowingly evil since she didn't have a
knowledge of Good and Evil yet thus
we're not only being punished for a sin
that we didn't commit we're being
punished for one which the person who
did commit it didn't do so knowing it
was wrong and was deceived into
committing imagine you were renting a
flat from a landlord and the landlord
decides to shut off your water supply
and your heating and installs a thousand
locks making it a torturous task just to
open the front door you ask him why are
you making me suffer like this and he
responds well don't you know that your
great grandfather used to rent this very
flat and he once committed an abominable
evil against me I'm just administering
the punishment but it's worse still
imagine if this so-called abominable
crime was something like this the
landlord had told your grandfather Once
Upon a Time don't flick that one switch
over there on the wall if you flick it
it's going to electrocute you and you'll
die
and then your grandfather's electrician
friend comes over and says look your
landlord doesn't know what he's talking
about it's clearly not going to
electrocute and kill you I mean the
thing's made of plastic and so your
grandfather looks at the switch and
decides to flick it and guess what his
electrician friend is right he didn't
die still the landlord was so outraged
that your grandfather flicked this
switch that he's now punishing you a
descendant for that crime and saying
that it's your own fault because hey
it's your family that broke the rules
and the worst part is that the
electrician friend is right the landlord
was actually lying to you and you're
still being punished I mean think about
it God says to Adam that if he eats the
fruit of the tree of the knowledge of
Good and Evil he will die that same day
the serpent says to Eve you're not gonna
die you're just going to become like God
and they both eat of the fruit
do they die
no do they become like God as the
serpent said that they will well let's
ask God God himself says at the end of
the Genesis narrative after they've
eaten the fruit the man has now become
like one of us knowing good and evil so
what God was lying and the serpent was
telling the truth and we're now being
punished because Adam and Eve took the
right advice and that's to say nothing
of the snake even the snakes of today
non-rational animals crawling around are
crueling as what a punishment for the
sin of some ancestral snake are we
supposed to also think that the problem
of animal suffering something that I
cover in the speech that Ken is
responding to but gets no mention from
him here is somehow a result of even
animals inheriting the punishments for
the behaviors of their forebears now of
course a great deal almost all perhaps
of the problems that I'm raising here
can be solved by oh I don't know perhaps
reading Genesis as an allegorical story
rather than a literal account of world
history in which Toil and childbirth are
literal punishments administered due to
a literal person eating a literal fruit
after a literal talking snake literally
convinced her to but that's not a live
option for Answers in Genesis god holds
everything together and he placed upon
us the curse of death and actually it
was a loving act it was an act of
judgment but also a loving it because
it's through death that he's able to
bring us back to him by paying the
penalty for our sins oh now we're really
talking God cursing us with death was
actually a loving act because it allowed
him to save us from that death via the
sacrifice of Jesus I think even most
Christians would cringe at this
interpretation for God so loved the
world that he created a problem in order
that he might solve it this would be
like me tying up a damsel to a train
track just so that I can then come and
save her from the approaching train oh
and I'm also the one driving the train
well maybe the punishment was needed
because without it there would be
nothing that Jesus could do to pay for
our sins without some punishment for him
to take on we'd be trapped in our sin
unable to inherit eternal life
well maybe but then at the end of
Genesis 3 God says the man has now
become like one of us knowing good and
evil he must not be allowed to reach out
his hand and take also from the Tree of
Life and eat and live forever so the
Lord God banished him from the Garden of
Eden so it seems like eternal life could
have been achieved by simply eating from
another tree but God didn't want this so
he employs cherubim and a flaming sword
to guard its fruits again as a metaphor
this is a fascinating and
thought-provoking narrative as a literal
account why on Earth would it be a
better option to produce a human sun to
brutally sacrifice when eternal life
could have been gained by simply eating
another piece of fruit so they don't
understand the gospel they don't
understand our sin what it's done to
this world and so they really don't
understand what's going on here and they
again look at God and blame God for
everything the biggest problem for
theism here is not famously the the
Great sense sufferings of the world like
holocausts or earthquakes but rather
meaning menial less significant
suffering like being caught out in the
rain or stubbing your toe or tripping
over a curve on the street
so alexo kind of goes on and says you
know that there's something that's even
more in in his opinion uh more difficult
to explain and that is why we would stub
our toe and and hurt our toe and so in
other words all the little things that
happen day to day but again he doesn't
understand we're living in a fallen
world this is not the world as God made
it you know god holds everything
together but he's not holding everything
together perfectly and so now everything
is falling apart and where to blame
where to blame for the fact that God
isn't holding everything together
perfectly how do you figure that it's
our sin see people don't want to take
responsibility for their sin they don't
want to acknowledge they're a sinner
they don't want to acknowledge they need
a savior and and again the interesting
thing is they look at this world and
they see all the death and suffering and
disease and so on and yet they attribute
this world to evolutionary process cases
and so what they're really saying is
it's great that Evolution did this uh
and then they turn around and say but if
if God's responsible for this how
horrible God is think of the
inconsistency even there
um Ken the difference is that
naturalists don't believe that the
evolutionary process is a conscious
agent that cares about the creatures it
produces you believe that God created
the world inserted within it an evil
snake knowing that he would be able to
seduce Adam and Eve and now punishes
their Descendants on account of their
original sin this must be reconciled
with his supposed loving nature
naturalists do not believe that
evolution is inflicting a punishment
upon animals they don't believe that the
suffering of the world must be
reconciled with some kind of loving
Essence at the basis of The evolutionary
process and also nobody says it's great
that Evolution did this in fact one of
the strongest Arguments for atheism is
the fact that the very mechanism by
which species evolved on planet Earth is
one brimming with torturous suffering
the violent and brutal survival of the
fittest we're not the ones claiming that
this world is being supervised Eyes by a
benevolent and all-powerful invigilator
you are we all agree that suffering
exists in the world but an evolutionary
worldview does not require that there's
some kind of moral justification for it
theism conversely does now an important
clarification is that I of course don't
think that Ken Ham's views here are
representative of Christianity as a
whole I guess what I'm mainly trying to
do here is demonstrate some of the
reasons why it seems ludicrous to me to
take Genesis to be a literal historical
account Ken Ham I would love to see you
respond to some of the questions that
I've raised in this video If you find
the time to the rest of you thanks for
watching and I'll see you in the next
one